The Scrap Heap

Poesy

Successive bards pursue Ambition’s fire
That shines, Oblivion, above thy mire.
The latest mounts his predecessor’s trunk,
And sinks his brother ere himself is sunk.
So die ingloriously Fame’s élite,
But dams of dunces keep the line complete.

Hospitality

Why ask me, Gastrogogue, to dine,
(Unless to praise your rascal wine)
Yet never ask some luckless sinner
Who needs, as I do not, a dinner?

Magnanimity

“To the will of the people we loyally bow!”
That’s the minority shibboleth now.
O noble antagonists, answer me flat—
What would you do if you didn’t do that?

Understated

“I’m sorry I married,” says Upton Sinclair:
“The conjugal status is awful!—
The devil’s device, a delusion and snare.”
Worse, far worse than that—it is lawful!

An Attorney-General

Philander Knox!—I know him by the sound;
His sleep, unlike his learning, is profound.
No dreams of duty mar his loud repose,
Nor strain the cobwebs tethering his nose,
Which, roaring ever like the solemn sea.
Proclaims to all the world that this is he.
In thought a tortoise but in act a hare,
Slow to decide and impotent to dare,
Yet no important crisis he ignores,
But sleeps upon it, and for action—snores.

Financial News

Says Rockefeller: “Money is not tight,”
And, faith, I’m thinking that the man is right.
If it were not, at least in morals, loose
He hardly could command it for his use.

Aspiration

No man can truthfully say that he would not like to be President.

William C. Whitney

Lo! the wild rabbit, happy in the pride
Of qualities to meaner beasts denied,
Surveys the ass with reverence and fear,
Adoring his superior length of ear,
And says: “No living creature, lean or fat,
But wishes in his heart to be like That!”

Democracy

Let slaves and subjects with extolling psalms
Before their sovereign execute salaams;
The freeman scorns one idol to adore—
Tom, Dick, and Harry and himself are four.

An Enemy to Law and Order

A is defrauded of his land by B,
Who’s driven from the premises by C.
D buys the place with coin of plundered E.
“That A’s an Anarchist!” says F to G.

Foresight

An “actors’ cemetery”! Sure
The devil never tires
Of planning places to procure
The sticks to feed his fires.

A Fair Division

Another Irish landlord gone to grass,
Slain by the bullets of the tenant class!
Pray, good agrarians, what wrong requires
Such foul redress? Between you and the squires
All Ireland’s parted with an even hand—
For you have all the ire, they all the land.

A Lacking Factor

“You acted unwisely,” I cried, “as you see
By the outcome.” He calmly eyed me:
“When choosing the course of my action,” said he,
“I had not the outcome to guide me.”

The Politician

“Let patriots manipulate
The tiller of the Ship of State;
Be mine the humble, useful toil
To work the tiller of the soil.”

Elihu Root

Stoop to a dirty trick or low misdeed?
What, bend him from his moral skies to it?
No, no, not he! To serve his nature’s need
He may upon occasion rise to it.

An Error

“I never have been able to determine
Just how it is that the judicial ermine
Is safely guarded from predacious vermin.”
“It is not so, my friend: though in a garret
’Tis kept in camphor, and you often air it,
The vermin will get into it and wear it.”

Vanished at Cock-Crow

“I’ve found the secret of your charm,” I said,
Expounding with complacency my guess.
Alas! the charm, even as I named it, fled,
For all its secret was unconsciousness.

Woman

Study good women and ignore the rest,
For he best knows the sex who knows the best.

A Partisan’s Protest

O statesmen, what would you be at,
With torches, flags and bands?
You make me first throw up my hat,
And then my hands.

A Bequest to Music

“Let music flourish!” So he said and died.
Hark! ere he’s gone the minstrelsy begins:
The symphonies ascend, a swelling tide,
Melodious thunders fill the welkin wide—
The grand old lawyers, chinning on their chins!

Oneiromancy

I fell asleep and dreamed that I
Was flung, like Vulcan, from the sky;
Like him was lamed—another part:
His leg was crippled and my heart.
I woke in time to see my love
Conceal a letter in her glove.

July Fourth

God said: “Let there be noise.” The dawning fire
Of Independence gilded every spire.

A Paradox

“If life were not worth having,” said the preacher,
“ ’Twould have in suicide one pleasant feature.”
“An error,” said the pessimist, “you’re making:
What’s not worth having cannot be worth taking.”

Reedified

Lord of the tempest, pray refrain
From leveling this church again.
Now in its doom, since so you’ve willed it,
We acquiesce. But you’ll rebuild it.

A Bulletin

“Lothario is very low,”
So all the doctors tell.
Nay, nay, not so—he will be, though,
If ever he get well.

An Inscription

For a Statue of Napoleon

A famous conqueror, in battle brave,
Who robbed the cradle to supply the grave.
His reign laid quantities of human dust:
He fell upon the just and the unjust.

An Erroneous Assumption

Good for he’s old? Ah, Youth, you do not dream
How sweet the roses in the autumn seem!

A Constructor

I saw the devil. He was working free—
A customs-house he builded by the sea.
“Why do you this?” The devil raised his head:
“Of churches I have built enough,” he said.

God Complies

“By prayer see Megapomp restored,”
Shouts Martext, pious creature.
Yes, God by supplication bored
From every droning preacher.
Exclaimed: “So be it, tiresome crew;
But I’e a crow to pick with you.”

In Articulo Mortis

The paper presented he solemnly signed,
Gasping—perhaps ’twas a jest he meant:
“This of a sound and disposing mind
Is the last illwill and contestament.”

The Discoverers

My! how my fame rings out in ever zone—
A thousand critics shouting: “He’s unknown!”

Unexpounded

On Evidence, on Deeds, on Bills,
On Copyhold, on Loans, on Wills,
Lawyers great books indite;
The creaking of their busy quills
I’ve never heard on Right.

The Eastern Question

Looking across the line, the Grecian said:
“This border I will stain a Turkey red.”
The Moslem smiled securely and replied:
“No Greek has ever for his country dyed.”
While thus each patriot guarded his frontier,
The Powers stole all the country in his rear.

Two Types

Courageous fool!—the peril’s strength unknown.
Courageous man!—so conscious of your own.

To a Critic of Tennyson

Affronting fool, subdue your transient light;
When Wisdom’s dull dares Folly to be bright:
If Genius stumble in the path to fame,
’Tis decency in dunces to go lame.

Cooperation

No more the swindler singly seeks his prey;
To hunt in couples is the modern way—
A rascal, from the public to purloin,
An honest man to hide away the coin.

Humility

Great poets fire the world with fagots big
That make a crackling racket,
But I’m content with but a whispering twig
To warm some single jacket.

Strained Relations

Says England to Germany: “Africa’s ours.”
Says Germany: “Ours, I opine.”
Says Africa: “Tell me, delectable Powers,
What is it that ought to be mine?”

Exoneration

When men at candidacy don’t connive,
From that suspicion if their friends would free ’em,
The teeth and nails with which they did not strive
Should be exhibited in a museum.

After Portsmouth

Begirt with bombs that fall and flames that rise,
The Tsar, bewildered, stares. “Alas,” he cries,
“Life withholds joy and death denies release!
And Roosevelt would have me think this peace.”

A Voice from Pekin

“ ‘Empress of China’! I nor rule nor reign:
I wear the purple but to hide the chain—
Free only to hold back the open door
For foreign devils drunk upon my floor.”

A Pious Rite

On Maunday Thursday, as was good and meet,
The Emperor of Austria washed the feet
Of twelve poor men to show how humble he
For twenty minutes of the year could be.
O Thou, who trackest tenants of the throne
Through moral quagmires, make them wash their own.

Justice

She jilted me. I madly cried:
“The grave at least can hold her!”
Reflecting then that if she died
’Twould stop her growing older,
I pitilessly sheathed the knife
And sternly sentenced her to life!

At the Beach

List, England, to our words of scorn
For noblemen to title born!
Yet be thine eyes awhile depressed,
For one has turned his prow to-west,
And we, to catch his landing-line,
Are pickling all our shins in brine.

An Infraction of the Rules

A duel in France, and the victor pursued
By the dogs of the law, by the multitude,
By society’s fierce ill-will!
O what is the matter? The man was so rude,
That he made an attempt to kill I

Conversely

There’s grief in Belgrade, for no crown, it is said,
Is found for King Peter in all of the town.
How sad that he’s lacking a crown for his head!
How sweet were he lacking a head for his crown!

A Warning

Cried Age to Youth: “Abate your speed!—
The distance hither’s brief indeed.”
But Youth pressed on without delay—
The shout had reached but half the way.

Psychographs

Says Gerald Massey: “When I write, a band
Of souls of the departed guides my hand.”
How strange that poems cumbering our shelves,
Penned by immortal parts, have none themselves!

For Wounds

O bear me, gods, to some enchanted isle
Where woman’s tears can antidote her smile.

A Literary Method

His “Hoosier poems” Riley says he writes
Upon an empty stomach. Heavenly Powers,
Feed him throat-full: for what the wretch indites
Upon his empty stomach empties ours!

Back to Nature

Nathaniel, Julian, Hildegardy!
Sure the stock is far from hardy,
And the name once heard with awe
Now provokes the loud guffaw—
“Hawthorne” in the memory dear,
“Haw-haw-hawthorne” in the ear!

Rudolph Block

What parallel, neighbor, be pleased to expound
’Twixt Belgium’s king and you may be found?
Why this: if the cable dispatches are true
He lies on his deathbed. So would you.

Boycott

“This thing’s a bomb,” said Gompers, lighting
The fuse; “ ’twill blow them all a kiting!”
Well, now ’tis shattered all to pieces.
And Gompers but a spot of grease is.

To Her

O, Sinner A, to me unknown
Be such a conscience as your own!
To ease it you to Sinner B
Confess the sins of Sinner C.

Creation

God dreamed—the suns sprang flaming into place,
And sailing worlds with many a venturous race!
He woke—His smile alone illumined space.

Rebuke

When Admonition’s hand essays
Our greed to curse,
Its lifted finger oft displays
Our missing purse.

Prayer

Fear not in any tongue to call
Upon the Lord—He’s skilled in all.
But if He answereth my plea
He speaketh one unknown to me.

The Long Fear

Noting the hangman’s frown and the law’s righteous rage,
Our murderers live in terror till they die of age.

An Inspired Performance

The Devil troubled a pool of mud,
And Vierick from out the smother
Arose and to prove his royal blood
Defamed his peasant mother.
Dear Devil, his poems—we’ll suffer all those,
But do not again provoke him to prose.

Sepulture

“Let’s bury the hatchet,” said Miller to Platt;
And Platt said to Miller: “I’ll gladly do that.”
On its grave, Warner Miller, the grasses grow not,
But the wind in your hair whistles over the spot.

Uncollected Verse

Basilica

With aimless feet, along the verge
Of ocean, where the rocks emerge,
I strolled, and watched the baffled surge.

In sheltered channels at my feet,
The sleepy ripples crisping neat,
Slid in and out with sluicy beat.

The groaning sea, wind-smitten white—
The day, shot through with throbbing light,
Lay palpitating on my sight.

From bloody death of stricken day,
And ocean’s leprous agony,
My weary eyes I drew away,

To where the rocks the margin mar
Of waters where the shadows are—
And saw the smiling of a star.

Imbedded deep in mossy green,
A glinting gem with lustrous sheen,
Burnt wondrous with a flame serene,

My soul grew drunken with its ray—
Like liquid April filing May,
Its wing-light suffused the day.

And day became—with colors cold
New-drowned in beauties manifold—
An opal chalice brimming gold.

A silent music clove the air—
A spirit bent in worship there—
My wish had wrought itself a prayer.

“O, if thy beauty, radiant stone,
Be not rejected love alone,
By wooing skies upon thee thrown;

But rather a desire intense,
Appealing thus to human sense
With more than human eloquence;

If so thou strivest to impart
The aspirations at thy heart—
Pulsing a wish with every spark;

Give me to claim thy sacred ray,
I’ll bear the from thy shades away,
And set the in the perfect day.

I’ll niche thee in a shrine made fair
With wondrous woods and metals rare,
And dim with amber-tinted air.

And sculpted work of quaint device,
Gem-tinct with gleams of prismic ice—
And lamps antique of fabled price—

And droning troops of monkish bees,
With censers filled at spicy trees,
Shall minister on bended knees.”

Grey darkness fell upon the land,
With hasty clutch my eager hand
To snatch the gem from barren strand

Essayed. When, Lo! with stiffened hair—
And vision smit with baleful glare—
And hope sharp-freezing to despair,

With heart compressed as in a vice,
And forehead bound with sudden ice—
I grasped a hidden Cockatrice.

O, with Heart of Stone with eyes of light,
And ivory throat of pallid white,
And snaky folds concealed from sight—

With jeweled teeth, alas! and breath
Whose touch to passion ministreth—
Sweet-spiced with aromatic death!

No pen of poison, gall-immersed,
Of deadly sins can name thy worst;
Or fitly curse thy race accursed.

San Francisco, Sept. 16th 1867.

A Mystery

A thing to be thought with abated breath,
And named with tears.
There ever shall be as there ever have been,
Beyond our ken,
The weight of the Past with its burden of sin,
A shadow thrown from the Future within,
On the souls of men.
And the weight unfelt and the shadow unseen,
With the cry of the Present unheard between,
Is all of life.
And ’tis only through toil and the nameless pain
Of wishes forever unwished again,
By an aimless strife—
As who should do battle with weapon of steel
To the fleshless Dark which he cannot feel,
As it hedges him round—
That peace is found.
Thinkst thou that “to smile” is the same as “to live,”
That a life shall receive what it need not give,
That toil is toil;
That a fruitful future unmoistened by tears,
Brings harvest of ears,
And wine and oil?
O, Dreamer of Dreams, there forever shall be
A blossomless growth in the spirit of thee,
Still draping in gloom.
Each fairy facade of each castle so fair,
By thy fancy upreared in the roseate air,
As ivy a tomb.
’Tis rooted in life and its fruit is of death,
And the prisoned breath,
In its baleful shadow, still shudders and moans
In voiceless tones.
Wouldst thou know, O mortal, the secret of Pain?
’Tis the payment in blood for each wish we obtain.

San Francisco, November 18th, 1867.

Rosalie

Lithesome, blithesome daughter mine,
Lift to me those lips of thine;
Greet me with those eyes of blue,
Eyes which seem to look me through:
Flashing now with life and light;
Now in hush of sleep reposing,
Veiled by lashes dark as night—
Shadows over violets closing.
Come thou, o’er me softly bow,
Shower on me fond caresses;
O’er my cheek, and on my brow,
Fling thy wealth of sunbright tresses.
Every throbbing pulse of mine
Beats in time and tune to thine;
All my heart’s tide sets to thee,
Loving little Rosalie.

As the dewdrop doth the flower,
As the sunshine doth the hour,
So the music of thy voice
Makes my soul rejoice.
All the livelong day around
Babbles on thy childlike chatter;
Mingled with the pleasant sound
Comes thy little foot’s light patter.
Like the linnet’s on the thorn
Joyously thy carol floweth—
Sing, my bird, for thy young morn
No dark night of winter knoweth.
Blue-eyed romp, in ceaseless whirl,
Half the angel, half the girl,
All the child art thou to me,
Laughing little Rosalie.

Loved one mine, the sunny day
Passeth rapidly away;
All too soon the bright time goes—
All too fast life’s current flows.
Now its fairy waters glide
Where the sunbeams o’er it quiver;
Soon the salt waves meet its tide,
Soon the beck will be the river—
Thine is now the primrose spring,
Thine the bluebell in the meadows:
Mine the fading hours that fling
Autumn leaves and lengthening shadows;
Yet my day lights up awhile
’Neath the sunshine of thy smile—
Thou dost bring new life to me,
Lithesome, blithesome Rosalie.

To Thee, My Darling

The heliotrope’s fragrant breath—
The subtle sweet of jasmine on the evening air—
The flowery mead, all radiant
With sympathetic pleasure
From the glowing kiss with which
The God of Day salutes its lovely face—
The whispering, snowy surf, wherewith
Old Ocean in his kindliest mood
Murmurs soft secrets to the willing sands—
The mingled joy and anguish thrilling us
In the weird plaints of Schubert—
Great Rossini’s heaven-born strains—
All graceful, lovely things,
Lifting my soul to beatific state—
Mnemosyne with flowery fetters
Binds to thee, my darling.

Serenade

Listen, maiden, to my strain,
Listen, pray thee, do!
Darkness shrouds the gloomy plain,
And our moon is on the wane,
Yet this fog cools not my brain,
’Tis on fire anew.

List! and from thy couch arise,
Rise, dear, pray thee do!
Not to gaze on murky skies,
That were now nor well nor wise,
But because your lover tries
To catch sight of you!

Draw that dismal curtain back—
Draw it back, duck, do!
’Tis like these clouds, whose flimsy rack
Hides yon bright moon’s silvery track,
I’d rather see the window black,
And know it bright to you.

Let me see those love-lit eyes—
Let me, sweet; now, do-o-o!
Lit by them these misty skies
Ne’er would wish the moon to rise,
And the stars, like scared fire-flies,
Would hide deep in the blue.

Come, dear, dup that tiresome door—
Dup the door, duck, do-oo-o!
Let me love afar no more,
Singing in the fog’s a bore,
Sooth to say my throat is sore,
Hoarse I’m getting too.

Let me to thy chamber creep,
Let me creep up, do-oo-oo!
I’ll not again disturb thy sleep,
Nor more before thy window weep,
Listen, love, and do not keep
Me longer in the dew.

Listen, maiden, to my song,
Listen, now come, do-oo-oo-oo!
Do not deem my rhyming wrong,
I’m not of the ribald throng,
Let me in, I merely long
To read my rhymes to you.

San Francisco, March 16, 1870.

Science

The winds of heaven trample down the pines
Or creep in lazy tides along the lea;
Lead the wild waters from the smitten rock.
Or crawl with childish babble to the sea;
But why the tempests out of heaven blow,
Or what the purpose of the seaward flow,
No man hath known, and none shall ever know.

Why seek to know? To follow nature up
Against the current of her course, why care?
Vain is the toil; he’s wisest still who knows
All science is but formulated prayer—
Prayer for the warm winds and the quickening rain,
Prayer for sharp sickle and for laboring swain.
To gather from the planted past the grain.